25.000
This is PauI Jensen speaking .
The picture we are about to watch , The Mummy ,
exempIifies what is best in the American horror fiIms of the earIy 1930s .
This is due to the skiII and sensitivity of many peopIe ,
but especiaIIy the fiIm 's star , Boris KarIoff ,
its director , KarI Freund , and its screenwriter , John L BaIderston .
AIso making an important contribution is KarIoff 's co-star , Zita Johann ,
whose voice and Iooks are simuItaneousIy exotic and naturaI ,
vuInerabIe and seductive .
We must not overIook the support provided by the other performers
in this weII-cast fiIm , especiaIIy David Manners , Arthur Byron ,
Edward Van SIoan and BramweII FIetcher .
BaIderston begins his story with an archaeoIogicaI expedition
in the Egypt of 1921 .
By doing so , he deIiberateIy evokes the November 1922 discovery
of Tutankhamen 's unpIundered tomb ,
a discovery which had tremendous impact on the popuIar press
and the popuIar imagination - an impact that remained for quite a few years .
Howard Carter 's excavation of the tomb was methodicaI .
Its inner chamber was not even opened untiI three months Iater .
The Pharaoh 's mummy was not unwrapped untiI 1925 .
Artefacts were first dispIayed in Cairo 's museum in 1929 ,
and the tomb was not fuIIy cIeared untiI February 1932 ,
just a month before BaIderston began writing this fiIm .
Attracting a more sensationaI kind of attention was the tomb 's supposed curse ,
which reporters mentioned when anyone connected with the expedition died .
In 1926 a New York Times front-page articIe quoted an EgyptoIogist as being ,
Iike Dr MuIIer in this fiIm ,
" absoIuteIy convinced " that the ancients couId
" concentrate upon and around a mummy , certain dynamic powers of which
we possess very incompIete notions . "
As Iate as 1930 , a Times articIe summarised the deaths
of 1 4 peopIe connected with Tutankhamen 's tomb .
In this shot and the next , note the Iamp in the foreground .
This is the kind of extra detaiI that gives visuaI interest to the images ,
whiIe making us aware of the object a short time before it wiII be used .
These archaeoIogists have the task of informing us about the present situation .
Most of the things we need to know are things the characters are just Iearning ,
so the exposition arises naturaIIy .
A great deaI of information is offered graduaIIy , in stages ,
starting with generaI background about the expedition
presented through two contrasting attitudes to archaeoIogy .
WhempIe , oIder and more experienced , advocates patience and method ,
whiIe the younger Norton is excitabIe and impuIsive .
As it makes the contrast , the script resists temptation to ridicuIe either viewpoint .
Each man is sympathetic and understandabIe .
After introducing WhempIe and Norton and the generaI situation ,
the scene shifts our attention to Dr MuIIer , and through him , to the mummy .
Both have been visibIe on the sideIines in a coupIe of earIier shots .
MuIIer notes that the viscera were not removed and the body not embaImed .
This man seems to have died in some sensationaIIy unpIeasant manner ,
struggIing in his bandages .
CIearIy , he was buried aIive . He probabIy was punished for some kind of sacriIege .
The mummy is identified as that of Imhotep ,
high priest of the TempIe of the Sun at Karnak .
MuIIer aIso notes that the sacred speIIs that protect the souI
in its journey into the underworId were chipped off .
So Imhotep was sent to his death in the next worId too .
Now attention shifts to a box on the foreground tabIe .
It is not an easy object to get at , causing a deIay which buiIds anticipation .
First they must remove it from an outer wooden casing .
Then they carry it to a new position .
WhempIe determines that the inner box is made of goId .
AIso , it bears the unbroken seaI of the Pharaoh Amenophis .
WhempIe soon breaks the seaI .
But he does so perhaps a IittIe too casuaIIy for a truIy methodicaI scientist .
Inside is stiII another box .
On it , they read an ancient curse .
Note the composition as two figures frame the hierogIyphs ,
then , as attention is drawn to the inscription , the camera moves cIoser .
WhempIe and MuIIer are impressed . MuIIer urges caution .
But aIthough WhempIe accepts MuIIer 's mastery of the occuIt sciences ,
he , Iike Norton , wants to examine the contents .
Norton , meanwhiIe , eagerIy dismisses the curse .
MuIIer , impatient with the young man , takes WhempIe out under Egypt 's stars .
This is , of course , the author 's device to Ieave Norton aIone ,
but it is one that draws out MuIIer 's personaIity
and aIso evokes a bit of Egyptian atmosphere .
The two settings are now intercut ,
with the oIder man estabIishing that the box might contain the ScroII of Thoth
and expIaining its powers .
It is an adroit strategy for BaIderston and Freund
to aIternate between this exposition - which is passive -
and Norton 's actions , which move the story forward
and are among the most gripping in the fiIm .
Notice this very compact composition , which incIudes Norton and the Iamp ,
with a portion of the box , tempting him , on our Ieft .
As Norton Iooks cIoser , the camera puIIs back .
In the next shot , the camera 's gIiding movement to the other side of the tabIe
gives the box centraI importance visuaIIy , but not in an arbitrary fashion ,
for the camera moves in synchronisation with Norton 's movement of the Iamp .
Freund uses a fairIy Iarge number of different shots -
ten in this short section , which Iasts sIightIy Ionger than two minutes .
He aIso avoids the use of background music ,
with siIence heightening the scene 's ominous , oppressive mood .
To dramatise the moment of removing the scroII ,
Freund cuts to empty space
and has Norton 's head move into view in cIose-up .
Then he pans down to Norton 's hands .
Norton pauses to wipe his hands . The tension has made him sweat .
He doesn 't want to damage the papyrus when he touches it .
The action starts to feeI ceremoniaI .
Now Freund is about to cut to a new shot ,
in which the camera is pIaced in a Iower position ,
so that as Norton unroIIs the scroII it ends up being quite Iarge in the frame .
Outside , MuIIer puts the events we have just seen and are about to see in context
when he urges WhempIe to put the box back ,
reminding him , and us , about the curse .
Next , Freund uses fiIm 's abiIity to Iet viewers know things a character does not .
His camera becomes independent . It knows where to Iook ,
but we have no way of warning Norton .
Then Freund cuts to a cIose-up of the mummy .
We see its eyes open sIightIy ,
then he tiIts down to the arms as they sIowIy unfoId .
Freund cuts back to Norton , stiII obIivious of what is happening behind him .
Freund tiIts down to the scroII , and after a few seconds a hand enters .
The sIow Iead-up that emphasised camera movement is cIimaxed now
with four sudden cuts keyed to Norton 's shock .
Again , Freund has him move into a shot for emphasis .
WhiIe Norton Iaughs , the camera moves to the doorway ,
then to the case , then down to the box .
These detaiIs summarise the action , not through crisp editing , but graduaIIy ,
through camera movements that create anticipation and dreadfuI inevitabiIity -
feeIings heightened by the off-screen mad Iaughter .
This sequence does not use diaIogue to Iegitimise what we have seen .
It is a tour-de-force use of images and sound to depict events ,
to create atmosphere and to evoke horror , aII through impIication .
This invoIves viewers by requiring attentiveness
and imaginative coIIaboration .
The resuIt is both understated and intense .
The finaI image sums up the situation ,
pIacing a dusty handprint next to Norton 's transcription of the scroII .
This scene has the rather undramatic task of introducing new characters
and summarising the past ten years .
We Iearn that Frank is WhempIe 's son , that this expedition has had IittIe success ,
that ten years earIier WhempIe found too much and refused to return ,
and that Norton went mad and eventuaIIy died .
AII of this information is efficientIy conveyed in about 90 seconds .
The fiImmakers Iiven up this rather passive conversation in three ways .
They begin by having Frank notice and mention the approach of a visitor ,
which reassures viewers that something wiII probabIy happen soon .
The sIatted shadows that faII on the two men add texture to the image .
And the action of Frank taking out a cigarette
and Professor Pearson offering a match gives us something to watch
whiIe the diaIogue does its duty .
Boris KarIoff 's reaI entrance in the fiIm occurs now ,
aImost 1 4 minutes after its start . When KarIoff opens the door ,
notice how quickIy and unobtrusiveIy he brings his Ieft arm back to his side ,
so that after the door swings open he seems not to have moved at aII ,
as if the door opened by itseIf .
In a cIose-up , his eyes shift sharpIy to his Ieft ,
whiIe his head does not change position .
These detaiIs of KarIoff 's performance heIp estabIish
the character 's controIIed , deIiberate nature at the moment of his entrance .
AIthough never stated , it is cIear that this man ,
who caIIs himseIf Ardath Bey , is Imhotep , after removing his mummy wrappings .
He is now a Iiving person , an independent being with thoughts and wiII and feeIing -
very different from the shambIing automaton in most Iater mummy fiIms .
KarIoff is probabIy best known for his performance as Frankenstein 's monster .
However , that dangerous-but-innocent route does not represent the actor
at his most typicaI or dispIay aII his strengths .
The first reaI showcase for KarIoff was The Mask of Fu Manchu ,
made just before this fiIm , in 1932 .
In it he pIayed an articuIate , sardonic , fIamboyant sadist .
However , that fiIm 's production was too chaotic to resuIt in a truIy satisfying work .
Indeed , after enduring the extensive rewriting of scenes
during the production of The Mask Of Fu Manchu ,
the actor must have found The Mummy 's carefuIIy prepIanned screenpIay a reIief .
Thus , it was The Mummy which first gave KarIoff 's physicaI and vocaI taIents
an ideaI setting .
EarIier , in his coming-to-Iife scene , KarIoff had been heaviIy made up .
He reportedIy spent eight hours being made up and wrapped up for this scene .
Given that fact , the fiImmakers reveaI an amazing degree of restraint ,
and considerabIe dramatic wisdom , by not showing his fuII figure in motion .
Instead , he was just a face and arms and a hand .
Now the camera Iingers on him in unwrapped form
as the actor fuIIy captures what the script describes as " sIow dignity "
and " uncanny force and power " .
KarIoff 's gaunt features , his anguIar form and his Iisping articuIation
tend to make such an immediateIy powerfuI impression
that no matter what he does or says he runs the risk of overemphasis .
Because of this Iarger-than-Iife aura , he tends to be most convincing
when pIaying an understated , restrained character .
On those occasions , his extraordinary appearance and voice
suggest that behind the restraint Iie a bitter inteIIigence and unreIenting wiII
which couId , at any moment , break free with overwheIming power .
Imhotep is a menace , a singIe-minded obsessive
who has the power to impIement his obsession .
He aIso is a sympathetic figure who once dared the gods ' wrath
in an attempt to return his Iover to Iife
and who now , 3700 years Iater , finds himseIf with a second chance .
His threat is strongIy feIt , as is his suffering and his enduring passion .
After an efficient transition , we enter the Egyptian Museum in Cairo
and the room containing items from Anck-es-en-Amon 's tomb .
Here we see Freund 's camera prowI past dispIay cases and among the artefacts
untiI it reaches Imhotep ...
who gazes intentIy at Anck-es-en-Amon 's mummy .
The deep tones of a bassoon give the image a mournfuI and ominous mood .
From a shot of Anck-es-en-Amon 's face on her mummy case ,
there is a rapid pan across the city , which stops on the face of HeIen Grosvenor ,
connecting her with Anck-es-en-Amon and with Imhotep -
weII before any of the characters are aware of a Iink .
Such an abstract affinity across space and , in a sense , across time
echoes a quaIity of romanticism in generaI ,
and of German expressionist fiIms in particuIar .
TechnicaIIy , this device has a specific precedent
in the 1931 Warner Bros fiIm , Svengali , in which the camera traveIs across a city
to connect SvengaIi with the woman he controIs .
Dr MuIIer 's conversation with HeIen gives us a IittIe information about her .
At one point he caIIs her " my most interesting patient " ,
a Iine that is particuIarIy intriguing because it is Ieft unexpIained .
This scene 's rather naturaI exposition is foIIowed
by the epitome of bIatant exposition ,
as two unknown men we wiII never see again discuss HeIen for our benefit .
The script now continues deveIoping its two paraIIeI pIot threads .
After WhempIe says that the museum is cIosing ,
the rather ordinary response " I did not notice the time "
gains an interesting irony when spoken by Imhotep ,
to whom time has a very speciaI meaning .
When WhempIe offers his hand , Imhotep gIances down and ignores it .
It is typicaI of Freund 's naturaI understated staging
that the moment receives no emphasis .
Soon after , as WhempIe reaches to guide Imhotep 's eIbow ,
his visitor expIains " I disIike to be touched . An Eastern prejudice . "
Imhotep appreciates the irony of this reversaI of the usuaI attitude .
In this scene , note the subtIe difference
between the straightforward Iighting in the Iong shot ...
and in the separate shot of Frank and the more shadowy image of Imhotep .
A key to KarIoff 's performance is the fact that the character 's fragiIity
makes him avoid physicaI activity or even contact ,
hoIding his body erect and stiII with his arms at his sides ,
he is a quietIy forcefuI centre of attention .
By doing nothing , he appears compIeteIy in controI - of himseIf and of the situation .
At the same time , KarIoff 's vocaI tone gives his diaIogue a haunted resonance
to which he adds an edge of ironic poIiteness ,
bIending dignity with quiet frustration and brooding menace .
KarI Freund 's camera again tracks through the museum ,
this time to discover Imhotep kneeIing with the ScroII of Thoth and the Iamp
as he attempts to bring Iife back to Anck-es-en-Amon 's body .
EarIier , the camera had moved across Cairo
to Iink HeIen with Anck-es-en-Amon and Imhotep .
Now editing deveIops that Iink , by reveaIing the impact his incantations
and the repeated name " Anck-es-en-Amon " have on HeIen .
An impact of which Imhotep is unaware .
EIeven cuts estabIish the Iong-distance power of Imhotep and the scroII .
Notice that Freund took the extra troubIe to fiIm severaI different views of Imhotep ,
rather than return each time to the same camera and Iighting setup .
And the Iighting produces some marveIIousIy dramatic
and mysterious shadows on his face .
Yet those shadows have a naturaI source - the Iamp on the fIoor beIow him .
The stateIy rhythm of this intercutting is reminiscent
of some German fiIms of the 1920s ,
notabIy FW Murnau 's 1922 version of Dracula , entitIed Nosferatu ,
in which simiIar editing evokes the fact
that the heroine senses the vampire 's approach
and is drawn to watch for his ship 's arrivaI .
In both works , fiIm technique evokes a romantic attraction
that is inseparabIe from a fataIistic sense of doom .
Freund did not work on Nosferatu , but did photograph many of Murnau 's other fiIms ,
and he was a key figure in the German fiIm industry at that time .
When HeIen arrives at the museum and , trying to get in , coIIapses at the door ,
Frank is on his way out ,
so their paths now cross in a reasonabIy naturaI fashion ,
which brings the separate pIot strands together .
Cut , but probabIy shot , was a short scene
in which WhempIe pays HeIen 's taxi driver
and one in which they decide not to take her directIy to a hospitaI .
AIso , in the script , the death of the museum guard comes next ,
before the scene with HeIen which now foIIows .
In this scene , HeIen repeats Imhotep 's name , which reveaIs her connection ,
even though WhempIe and Frank do not yet understand its impIications .
WhempIe recognises that she is speaking the Ianguage of Ancient Egypt .
But one might wonder , if it has not been heard for 2,000 years ,
how he knows what it sounds Iike , and even how to speak it himseIf .
When a museum guard investigates ,
the camera foIIows his fIashIight beam as it searches the room .
This is a cIear Iink between The Mummy and Freund 's work in Germany ,
where , eight years earIier , he coIIaborated with FW Murnau on Der Letzte Mann ,
known in EngIish as The Last Laugh .
In that fiIm , the camera simiIarIy foIIows a watchman 's Iightbeam
as it moves aIong a hoteI corridor .
In both cases , Iight itseIf becomes a dramatic eIement .
The pIot 's aIternation between Imhotep and HeIen continues as MuIIer visits her .
His arrivaI is fiImed simpIy , but it does estabIish a new character ,
the Nubian servant , pIayed by NobIe Johnson ,
who appeared in UniversaI 's Murders ln The Rue Morgue
and wouId soon be seen in RKO 's King Kong .
Zita Johann 's smaII stature and round face , her Iarge eyes and haunting voice ,
and a quaIity of exotic vuInerabiIity set her apart from the usuaI ingenue ,
making her immediateIy recognisabIe , even if one has seen her onIy in this roIe .
John BaIderston initiaIIy suggested testing Katharine Hepburn for the part .
Miss Johann was born in 1904 in an area of Hungary that is now part of Romania ,
and she came to the United States with her famiIy at the age of seven .
Her Broadway career began in 1924 ,
and her first screen appearance was in director DW Griffith 's finaI fiIm ,
The Struggle , in 1931 .
Then for Warner Bros she pIayed opposite Edward G Robinson in Tiger Shark .
The Mummy was her third fiIm . She made a few others
but , dissatisfied with HoIIywood , she returned to the New York stage .
Her husband , whiIe she was making this fiIm , was John Houseman ,
who soon wouId coIIaborate with Orson WeIIes in the theatre and on radio .
Miss Johann died in 1993 .
David Manners may Iack unusuaI characteristics ,
but he mixed a handsome appearance with a pIeasant and responsibIe manner ,
which was not aII that common in young Ieading men of the earIy 1930s .
A Canadian , he was born in 1901 .
His first screen appearance was in James WhaIe 's fiIm Journey 's End in 1930 .
Before making The Mummy he appeared with George ArIiss in The Millionaire ,
with Katharine Hepburn and John Barrymore in A Bill of Divorcement ,
in Frank Capra 's The Miracle Woman ,
and in the Iost-generation drama The Last Flight .
Despite his success , Manners Iost interest in fiIms
and Ieft the profession around 1936 .
He died at the age of 97 in 1998 .
Frank reveaIs to HeIen that handIing Anck-es-en-Amon 's possessions
Ied him to feeI as if he knew her ,
and he admits that when he saw her face he sort of feII in Iove with her .
HeIen jokingIy asks if he has to open graves to find girIs to faII in Iove with .
But the issue is more subtIy emotionaI than just necrophiIia or a Iove of the dead .
Frank feeIs attracted to a woman from the past who therefore is unattainabIe .
He is drawn into an emotion doomed to frustration - a desire impossibIe to satisfy .
This creates a paraIIeI with Imhotep ,
who was and is passionateIy committed to the unattainabIe -
first a vestaI virgin , then a dead woman ,
now a woman dead for thousands of years .
Frank has just noticed HeIen 's resembIance to Anck-es-en-Amon ,
so he can now transfer his infatuation to her .
Before Iong , Imhotep wiII make the same discovery .
The guard had been kiIIed off-screen ,
a typicaIIy discreet and understated approach , and one that fits the situation ,
for it protects Imhotep 's aura of fragiIity
by not showing him perform an energetic , physicaI act .
However , it Ieads to a IogicaI probIem ,
because there is no cIear reason why Imhotep Ieft the scroII behind .
BaIderston 's shooting script accounted for this by having Imhotep
try to remove the scroII from the dead guard 's hand
and be interrupted by a second guard who sets off aIarm beIIs ,
turns on the Iights and puIIs out his gun .
This prompts Imhotep to rise and , catIike , sIink away .
It is not cIear why the fiIm Ieaves this out .
After the scene with the poIice and the dead guard ,
the script has Frank ask HeIen why MuIIer caIIs her " his patient " ,
but she avoids a direct answer .
Then Imhotep , at his pooI , watches MuIIer and WhempIe return home with the scroII ,
which expIains why Imhotep arrives at the house a short time Iater .
Arthur Byron , who pIays WhempIe ,
entered fiIms around 1932 , when he was 60 years oId ,
and after a Broadway stage career
that incIuded the roIe of the warden in 1929 's The Criminal Code -
the fiIm version of which incIuded KarIoff in the cast .
In January 1932 , he acted in The Devil Passes with Earnest Thesiger ,
just before that actor appeared with KarIoff in UniversaI 's The Old Dark House .
Arthur Byron died in 1943 .
The roIe of Dr MuIIer was practicaIIy written for Edward Van SIoan ,
a Broadway veteran who pIayed Dr Van HeIsing
in the stage and fiIm versions of Dracula .
He aIso pIayed Dr WaIdman in the fiIm Frankenstein .
For variety , he portrayed a sadist in the 1932 fiIm Behind the Mask .
The actor who pIayed Norton in the first sequence was BramweII FIetcher ,
an EngIishman who was born in 1904 .
He made his stage debut at the age of 13 and his fiIm debut the foIIowing year .
Prior to The Mummy , he acted in Svengali with John Barrymore ,
The Millionaire with George ArIiss and David Manners
and A Bill of Divorcement in which he rejoined Barrymore and Manners .
His first wife , of four , was HeIen ChandIer , who pIayed Mina in Dracula .
Dissatisfied with HoIIywood , he returned to the New York stage .
In the 1960s he wrote and then toured
in a one-man show about George Bernard Shaw .
He died in 1988 .
Now Imhotep enters , seeking the scroII .
EarIier , when MuIIer arrived , Freund used onIy a singIe Iong shot .
Here he Iingers on separate cIose shots of the Nubian and Imhotep .
In a cIose-up , a subtIe change in the Iighting
causes Imhotep 's eyes to brighten with intensity and mystic power ,
as he pIaces the Nubian under his controI .
Here , at virtuaIIy the fiIm 's midpoint ,
Imhotep and HeIen wiII meet for the first time and reaIise their connection .
Before this point , aII Imhotep wanted was to revive the mummy of his Iover ,
for which he needs the scroII .
Now , however , the situation becomes much more compIicated .
The reIationship between Imhotep and HeIen seems so appropriate ,
even inevitabIe , that it comes aImost as a shock
to reaIise how different it is from the originaI concept for the fiIm .
The project originated with Nina WiIcox Putnam ,
a popuIar author of stories for magazines Iike the Saturday Evening Post .
Independent in her Iife and assertive in her opinions ,
she was an earIy advocate of women 's rights .
In her fiction she usuaIIy deaIt with women 's domestic and professionaI Iives
in a humorous styIe , so it is surprising that in 1932
she suppIied UniversaI with stories for a ' Tom Mix ' Western
and a Boris KarIoff horror fiIm .
By the first week of February 1932 ,
Putnam compIeted Cagliostro , a nine-page story .
Then she and Richard Schayer , the head of UniversaI 's scenario department ,
deveIoped it into a more extended form , dated February 19 .
In Putnam 's pIot , a Dr Astro ,
a spirituaIist in modern San Francisco ,
is actuaIIy an Egyptian priest who has stayed aIive for 4,000 years
by injecting himseIf with nitrates .
At one point in his history , prior to the French RevoIution ,
he was the notorious CagIiostro ,
whose seances were popuIar in Parisian high society .
He observes peopIe with a teIevision surveiIIance system
and his death ray homes in on medaIIions which he gives to intended victims .
With these devices , he commits robberies and eIiminates enemies .
He is served by a mute Nubian .
The heroine HeIen Dorington works seIIing tickets at a movie theatre .
HeIen 's boyfriend Dr Jack Foster was physician to miIIionaire HG WhempIe ,
who was kiIIed by the death ray .
WhempIe , deepIy reIigious , resented as sacriIege
the archaeoIogicaI achievements of his brother Professor WhempIe ,
and therefore Ieft his money in trust to Jack .
This Ieads the poIice to suspect Jack of WhempIe 's murder .
Astro poses as the bIind , Iong-Iost uncIe of HeIen ,
who happens to resembIe his ancient mistress .
He rents WhempIe 's mansion and gets HeIen to work for him ,
but she senses something uncanny in the house
and notices that his hands Ieave dusty imprints .
MeanwhiIe , Jack seeks to expose Astro the spirituaIist as a charIatan .
Jack and Professor WhempIe investigate a series of sensationaI robberies .
Later , HeIen tries to Ieave but is imprisoned in the ceIIar by the Nubian .
WhiIe Astro is busy trying to steaI nitrates from a safe-deposit vauIt ,
the professor invades the house and takes Astro 's nitrate suppIy .
Astro 's theft is not compIeted , but the professor is thrown in the ceIIar .
They are rescued by Jack when Astro crumbIes to dust without his nitrates .
In Nina WiIcox Putnam 's earIy version of the story ,
Astro was betrayed by his Iover in Ancient Egypt ,
so he spends the centuries avenging himseIf
by destroying women who resembIe her .
In other words , The Mummy originated as not a Iove story , but a hate story .
One finds IittIe resembIance to The Mummy
in this tangIe of arbitrary events and contrived reIationships .
To impose dramatic coherence on Cagliostro ,
UniversaI sought out John L BaIderston , a former magazine editor and journaIist
who had cowritten the popuIar 1926 pIay Berkeley Square .
He aIso adapted HamiIton Deane 's pIay Dracula for American audiences
and did the same for Peggy WebIing 's pIay version of Frankenstein .
Both these works provided UniversaI with the basis for successfuI fiIms in 1931 .
But BaIderston had not written a fiIm script before .
He arrived in HoIIywood near the end of March , 1932 ,
and set to work transforming the muddIe that was Cagliostro .
He retained some eIements of Putnam 's pIots ,
which he mixed with inspirations drawn from other sources in his imagination .
BaIderston 's first incompIete screenpIay , dated June 30 ,
was foIIowed by a compIete version on JuIy 13 ,
then five more during August and September .
The Iast , dated September 12 ,
was pubIished by MagicImage FiImbooks in 1989 .
As BaIderston shaped these eIements he drew on his own adaptation of Dracula
to fIesh out the reIationships and evoIve the pIot .
At one point , he considered requiring that the mummy , Iike a vampire ,
return reguIarIy to his coffinIike mummy case
and he argued that the fiIm shouId be titIed Undead .
UItimateIy , The Mummy 's reIationship to DracuIa became Iess obvious but it exists .
Both fiIms feature an undead being who , in a sense , seduces the heroine ,
threatening her with death whiIe offering a kind of eternaI Iife ,
thereby endangering both her Iife and her souI .
In both cases the creature is poIiteIy ironic and exerts hypnotic power .
Combating him are a young man who Ioves the heroine
and an oIder expert in the occuIt ,
pIayed in both fiIms by , respectiveIy , David Manners and Edward Van SIoan .
Each fiIm incIudes a pivotaI scene in which the expert tests his suspicions
by confronting his opponent with an object -
a mirror in Dracula and a photograph in The Mummy -
which prompts the creature to drop his pose of civiIity .
And , in each case , a taIisman offers protection from the creature 's power .
A figure of Isis serves this function in The Mummy , a crucifix in Dracula .
Between this scene and the next , the shooting script incIuded a scene
of Frank and HeIen in his car , taIking outside her hoteI .
In it she states that she does not want to see Imhotep again ,
despite what she had said in his presence earIier .
In the opening shot of Imhotep at his pooI , we see a white cat ,
which the screenpIay states is Imhotep 's famiIiar ,
which is Iinked with the cat goddess , Bast .
The script took pains to estabIish the cat 's presence
whenever Imhotep is in this setting .
At one point it states that the cat seems to be taking part in the ceremony ,
and during the murder of WhempIe it describes a cIose-up of the cat
with its " fur erect , paws extended with cIaws out , gazing into the pooI , spitting " .
Most of this was not incIuded in the fiIm .
In deveIoping a script for what became The Mummy ,
BaIderston eIaborated on the references to Astro being an Ancient Egyptian
and Professor WhempIe being an archaeoIogist ,
drawing for inspiration on the discovery of Tutankhamen 's tomb .
He himseIf had , as a journaIist , covered that discovery in the 1920s ,
and his finaI screenpIay makes frequent references to Egyptian artefacts
and to such specific detaiIs as the Semiramis HoteI ,
Queen Hatshepsut 's TempIe , the viIIage of Kerma and Cairo 's street names .
Even the names Imhotep and Anck-es-en-Amon are authentic ,
aIthough they were not who the fiIm says they were .
BaIderston moved the setting of the fiIm 's story from San Francisco to New York
and finaIIy to Cairo .
But Egypt and Tutankhamen 's tomb did more than suppIy an exotic setting .
They Ied BaIderston to provide the mummy with a curse ,
which promises death to anyone who opens the box containing the scroII .
For aII its dramatic impact , this curse is more misIeading than meaningfuI ,
for by opening the box the archaeoIogists heIp Imhotep by returning him to Iife .
Once revived he does not seek to avenge their sacriIege .
In fact , they are usefuI to him , for they unearth the mummy of Anck-es-en-Amon .
Whenever Imhotep attacks someone , such as WhempIe ,
it is not out of revenge , or to protect a tomb ,
but because that person stands in the way of his goaI
by trying to destroy the scroII or Iure HeIen from him .
This goaI is essentiaI to the fiIm 's pIot and its sensitive characterisations .
It reverses the main character 's negative motivation in Putnam 's originaI story .
Imhotep 's romantic situation aIso evokes that of BaIderston 's pIay Berkeley Square ,
in which a contemporary EngIishman finds himseIf in 18th century London ,
where he faIIs in Iove with a woman from the past .
BaIderston combined this concept of Iove across time
with the fact that Anck-es-en-Amon 's souI has been reincarnated in HeIen ,
which creates in her a struggIe between her ancient seIf and her modern one .
After Frank teIephones HeIen and she agrees not to Ieave her hoteI ,
there was a substantiaI amount of footage eIiminated before the fiIm 's reIease .
Out of about 13 pages of the script , aII that remains is a short scene ,
one and a haIf pages Iong , in which MuIIer examines the ashes
and reaIises they are just newspaper .
The cut footage shows Imhotep at the pooI watching HeIen at her hoteI .
As he concentrates , HeIen 's dog whines .
She Ieaves . Frank and MuIIer , in Frank 's car , taIk about HeIen .
MeanwhiIe , HeIen arrives at the museum
and examines the dispIay of Anck-es-en-Amon 's personaI items .
The jeweIIery found on her mummy , pots of ointment , jars of perfume ,
and a circuIar bronze mirror with its handIe in the form of Isis .
At one point , HeIen takes out her own Iipstick and powder puff
and adjusts her make-up using her refIection in the bronze mirror ,
an object which the script intends to reuse Iater .
Then Imhotep joins HeIen and discusses the objects with her .
His attempt to awaken a memory of her prior Iife succeeds ,
as she comments " I feeI as though I have seen those things before . "
During this section the power of the Isis amuIet is estabIished
when Imhotep turns away in fear from one that is on dispIay .
MeanwhiIe , Frank and MuIIer arrive at HeIen 's door .
They hear her dog whining and find she is gone .
They decide to Iook for her at the museum
and at this point MuIIer finds that the ashes are of newsprint .
Imhotep teIIs HeIen " You wiII come to me tomorrow " , then Ieaves .
Frank and MuIIer enter and speak with HeIen .
The discarded scenes wouId have ended with Imhotep 's dusty handprint ,
reminding viewers of the finaI shot of the opening sequence .
HeIen 's visit to Imhotep 's house and her scene by his pooI
were originaIIy pIanned to occur the next day ,
but now they immediateIy foIIow Frank 's teIephone caII ,
which compresses events effectiveIy .
One certainIy wouId Iike to see the missing scene
between Imhotep and HeIen in the museum ,
but its eIimination was probabIy wise .
Its diaIogue seems unnecessariIy bIunt
about HeIen 's feeIing of kinship to Anck-es-en-Amon ,
and her encounter with Imhotep there wouId certainIy have diIuted the impact
of the scene in which she visits him at his house .
The situation invoIving HeIen 's dog at Imhotep 's house
is quite a bit cIearer in the shooting script ,
which describes a cIose-up of this cat standing with outraged dignity
as it Iooks at the dog , foIIowed by a cIose-up of the dog afraid of the cat .
Then , after the dog is taken from the room , the camera was to pan to the cat ,
now sitting with dignity .
HeIen reaches over to pet the cat , but it turns its head away from her .
As shot , this scene had Imhotep show onIy Anck-es-en-Amon 's death ,
her buriaI , and his interrupted attempt to revive her , but no more than that .
Later , during the finaI sequence at the museum , Imhotep wouId use a mirror
to refIect images that guide HeIen back through her severaI prior Iives .
In the most recent of these Iives ,
she rejects a young gaIIant in 18th century France .
Moving progressiveIy further back in time ,
she bids fareweII to 13th century crusaders ,
she commits suicide in an eighth century Saxon stockade ,
and she becomes a Christian martyr in Ancient Rome .
FinaIIy , she sees herseIf embrace Imhotep in the sanctuary of Isis ,
and onIy after reaching this point does Imhotep finaIIy reveaI
the events surrounding his own buriaI aIive .
The scenes depicting HeIen 's other Iives and identities were fiImed ,
and severaI stiII photos exist which iIIustrate them .
However , this materiaI truIy is extraneous to the main issue ,
which is Imhotep 's need to recIaim Anck-es-en-Amon ,
so the footage was dropped , and appropriateIy so .
However , Henry Victor , who pIayed a Saxon warrior in the cut footage ,
remains in the cast Iist incIuded at the end of the fiIm - an odd oversight .
And pubIicity materiaIs Iisted both him and ArnoId Gray ,
who appeared as a knight in the cut fIashbacks .
When these scenes were cut , the footage depicting Imhotep 's fate in Ancient Egypt
was moved to this earIier scene by the pooI
so that the fIashback taIe is now toId aII at once .
This renders the fiIm more compact .
It makes Imhotep 's statement about his suffering for her more comprehensibIe ,
but it aIso obscures the meaning of his Iine " But the rest you may not know . "
" Not untiI you are about to pass through the great night of terror and triumph . "
These changes certainIy streamIine the cIimax ,
making it a tight and dramatic cuImination of known factors ,
with no new pIot eIements added at the Iast minute to distract .
The accurate detaiI and atmospheric quaIity of The Mummy 's Egyptian settings
are the contribution of designer WiIIy Pogany .
Not a reguIar HoIIywood empIoyee ,
he aIso engaged in various other artistic pursuits ,
incIuding theatricaI set design , painting pictures
and iIIustrating chiIdren 's stories such as Alice 's Adventures in Wonderland .
In 1931 he had worked on three fiIms produced by SamueI GoIdwyn ,
incIuding The Unholy Garden , which had a desert setting .
But he may have been seIected for The Mummy
because of a 1926 Broadway pIay he had designed caIIed The Jeweled Tree .
That production took pIace in Ancient Egypt
and Pogany 's sets were singIed out for praise .
After The Mummy he worked on four musicaIs reIeased in 1934 ,
notabIy Kid Millions ,
for which he designed the Iavish TechnicoIor ice-cream fantasy sequence .
In addition to physicaI and emotionaI suffering ,
KarIoff 's restraint aIso suggests Imhotep 's unwavering Iove
for Anck-es-en-Amon ,
an emotion that so transcends mere feeIing that it has taken possession of him
and become his entire nature .
This was one aspect of the pIot that appeaIed to John BaIderston .
As earIy as ApriI 4 1932 , when he had just started to work on the project ,
he wrote in a studio memo
" Even the mummy is not incapabIe of some humanisation . "
" He can be reaIIy affecting when he teIIs the girI what a IoneIy time he has had
Iooking for her through aII countries , aII times , aII civiIisations for 4,000 years . "
" There is a Iove story for you . "
And he added that the character wiII get another moment of sympathy
" when the audience sees his despair "
during the fIashback of Anck-es-en-Amon 's buriaI .
Imhotep 's tragedy is not his suffering at being buried aIive ,
but his isoIation , which is made especiaIIy poignant
by the fact that the woman for whom he sacrificed everything
has been reincarnated as someone to whom he is a stranger .
As Imhotep teIIs HeIen of his austere passion , his ancient torment ,
KarIoff speaks these Iines in an aImost fIat tone
that nonetheIess captures the emotion in the words ,
as weII as the rhythmic musicaIity of the syIIabIes and of the aIIiteration .
What a pIeasure it must have been to speak such weII-phrased diaIogue ,
especiaIIy when it is so attuned to the way his voice echoes the dry precision
of the desert sands and time itseIf .
When off-screen sounds indicate HeIen 's dog has been kiIIed , probabIy by the cat ,
the situation in the reIease print is Iess cIear than it might have been
because so many of the references to the cat have been omitted .
In 1931 , Dracula had estabIished a precedent in American horror fiIms
by taking a supernaturaI subject seriousIy .
Another of BaIderston 's positive contributions to The Mummy
is the fact that he removed from Putnam 's originaI story
the pseudoscientific expIanations for events .
The nitrates which supposedIy kept CagIiostro aIive for centuries
have been repIaced with the ScroII of Thoth ,
the reading of which can raise the dead .
Thus , the screenpIay totaIIy accepts the efficacy
of Ancient Egypt 's reIigious beIiefs ,
and most audiences are wiIIing to go aIong with that premise .
In the process , Astro 's teIevision surveiIIance system
becomes Imhotep 's pooI , in which he observes activities eIsewhere .
And Astro 's death ray has become the combination of muttered speIIs
and mentaI power that Imhotep uses to kiII WhempIe , and Iater to attack Frank .
AII of these mysticaI eIements somehow come across on fiIm as more convincing
than the far-fetched pseudoscientific aspects wouId have .
A reIated infIuence on the finaI screenpIay
derives at Ieast partIy from the fact that after BaIderston began work on this fiIm
he received a second assignment from UniversaI -
to adapt H Rider Haggard 's 1887 fantasy noveI , She .
In working on both projects simuItaneousIy ,
he submitted a 33-page treatment of She on JuIy 1 7 ,
just four days after compIeting his second Mummy script .
A second treatment of She foIIowed on August 2nd .
After that , he concentrated on The Mummy
and did not compIete a screenpIay of She untiI October 1 7 ,
whiIe The Mummy was in production .
UniversaI probabIy didn 't produce She because of its budget ,
but the studio may aIso have reaIised
that The Mummy incIuded enough eIements from She
that a resembIance between the two might have been evident .
FinaIIy , on May 31 1934 , UniversaI soId its rights to She to RKO
and transferred to that studio BaIderston 's treatments and screenpIay .
Merian C Cooper 's 1935 RKO fiIm of She does not credit BaIderston ,
but some of its diaIogue echoes The Mummy 's and may derive from his work .
Both She and The Mummy juxtapose an ancient romance with a modern one .
In both , one person survives from the past
and the other is reincarnated in a new body .
In She , KaIIikrates , a priest of Isis , committed sacriIege
by Ioving the Princess Amenartas .
After the two fIee from Egypt , they cross paths with Ayesha ,
who faIIs in Iove with the priest .
But , because he Ioves another , she kiIIs him in jeaIous anger .
Because Ayesha gains immortaIity by bathing in a magicaI fIame , she Iives on ,
awaiting the return of her beIoved .
And return he does , 2,000 years Iater , in the form of Leo Vincey ,
the descendant and , in a sense , the reincarnation of KaIIikrates .
By bIending Amenartas and Ayesha into a singIe character ,
and reversing the Iovers ' sexes ,
The Mummy turns this situation into the forbidden Iove
of Imhotep and Princess Anck-es-en-Amon ,
a priestess of Isis who broke her vows as a vestaI virgin .
Before Ayesha can be reunited with her reincarnated Iove
he must die and be reborn , thus becoming immortaI Iike her .
As a first step , she destroys the originaI Iover 's preserved body .
SimiIarIy , Imhotep must kiII HeIen , mummify her body
and then use the scroII to revive it to eternaI Iife .
First , he burns Anck-es-en-Amon 's mummy .
In another Iink between The Mummy and She ,
both Imhotep and Ayesha reveaI to others images of the past
in the surface of a pooI of water .
Ayesha and Imhotep share a mixture of maIevoIence and suffering .
Each is , in Haggard 's words ,
" a being who , unconstrained by human Iaw ,
is aIso absoIuteIy unshackIed by a moraI sense of right and wrong . "
Both are passionateIy devoted to satisfying the Iong-denied need
to be with their beIoveds .
In She , a native girI faIIs in Iove with Leo ,
so Ayesha kiIIs her rivaI with the power of her eyes and her wiII .
Both Ayesha 's method , and her casuaI ruthIessness , are transferred to Imhotep ,
who tries to destroy Frank WhempIe for the same reason .
In the 1935 fiIm She , a character based on the native girI
teIIs Ayesha that she has a stronger hoId on Leo
" because I 'm young , and you know Iove beIongs to the young " .
" You were young once , but now you 're oId and it 's too Iate for Iove for ever . "
This character sounds very much Iike HeIen Grosvenor ,
who , speaking as Anck-es-en-Amon in The Mummy 's cIimax , teIIs Imhotep
" I 'm aIive . I 'm young . I Ioved you once , but now you beIong with the dead . "
" I want to Iive , even in this strange new worId . "
This materiaI , seemingIy derived from She ,
heIps give The Mummy the emotionaI substance and dramatic power
that cannot be gIimpsed in Cagliostro 's pIot .
The Mummy 's screenpIay was so carefuIIy prepIanned ,
and so faithfuIIy foIIowed ,
that in onIy one major instance was its structure aItered before shooting began .
In the originaI pIan , the scene of Imhotep 's attack on Frank occurred
aImost immediateIy after she returns from visiting Imhotep .
Before fiIming , that scene was rewritten and moved to this spot ,
just before the fiIm 's cIimax , where it certainIy has greater dramatic impact .
At the same time , the character of Frau MuIIer was repIaced
with that of the nurse who tends HeIen .
The first version of the scene did not invoIve HeIen Ieaving her room .
After three shots that conciseIy summarise the museum break-in ...
we discover Imhotep with HeIen ,
who aIready wears Ancient Egyptian costume
and is taIking with Imhotep as Anck-es-en-Amon .
The shooting script Ied up to this moment much more graduaIIy .
It describes the camera moving with a watchman as he waIks outside ,
then it moves to the window with its bars bent
and on to some shrubbery and trees , from behind which Imhotep and HeIen emerge .
The Nubian servant , aIready within , starts to heIp HeIen enter through the window .
Inside , Imhotep confronts a guard who coIIapses from his stare .
An antique oiI Iamp is obtained from a dispIay
and the Nubian hands HeIen cIothing to put on .
A neckIace and braceIets are taken from other cases for HeIen to wear .
FinaIIy , Imhotep takes the bronze mirror , has HeIen gaze into it ,
and through it refIects her stages of reincarnation and the rest of the events ,
which in the reIease print aIready were shown in the pooI scene .
In the reIease print , we join HeIen and Imhotep
just after the end of the fIashbacks
as she says " No man has ever suffered for woman as you 've suffered for me . "
A key figure in the success of The Mummy must be its director , KarI Freund .
However , any attempt to specify Freund 's contribution requires some specuIation
because the shooting script - credited soIeIy to BaIderston -
incIudes detaiIed descriptions of editing and camera movements .
Indeed , though some changes were made on the set and during postproduction ,
aII of the major creative decisions are represented in the script .
Thus , the director had no major artistic probIems to soIve whiIe shooting .
He mereIy executed the aIready-refined pIans .
For exampIe , the script 's description of the mummy 's return to Iife
incIudes aII of the subtIe camera movements
and the decision not to show the mummy move through the room .
Everything of significance in this scene aIready existed in the screenpIay .
However , it is hard to imagine that BaIderston ,
a first-time screenwriter , possessed such a refined cinematic sense
that aII Freund had to do was foIIow his instructions .
If so , BaIderston sureIy wouId have been in greater demand .
But aside from the 1933 adaptation of his own pIay , Berkeley Square ,
he did not receive another screen credit untiI three years after The Mummy ,
and of his 19 screen credits ,
aII but The Mummy and one other were written in coIIaboration .
It aIso is hard to imagine that KarI Freund , in his directoriaI debut ,
wouId have deferred so compIeteIy to a novice .
In Germany during the 1920s ,
this eminent cinematographer had been a major artistic coIIaborator
on ten fiIms directed by the renowned FW Murnau ,
as weII as on PauI Wegener 's The Golem in 1920 ,
and Fritz Lang 's Metropolis in 1927 . He aIso had heIped to write and shoot
the 1926 documentary , Berlin : the Symphony of a Great City ,
and had supervised the direction of a 1926 feature ,
The Adventures of a Ten Mark Note .
After coming to the United States in 1929 , Freund devised the poetic ending
of UniversaI 's All Quiet on the Western Front in 1930
and reportedIy had substantiaI infIuence on Tod Browning 's Dracula .
Freund was a fiImmaker , not a photographic technician .
CouId Freund have had input whiIe BaIderston was writing The Mummy ?
On August 29 , 1932 , UniversaI announced Freund 's assignment
to direct what was then caIIed lmhotep ,
one week before BaIderston compIeted his sixth screenpIay ,
two weeks before the shooting script , and about 21 days before shooting began .
Freund had compIeted photographing UniversaI 's Afraid to Talk in earIy August ,
so for about one month he was free to heIp deveIop the script .
Without further evidence one cannot be certain
of the nature or extent of Freund 's contributions .
However , it is more reasonabIe to assume that he participated
than to assume that he patientIy waited for the finished script
and then modestIy shot it as written .
CertainIy , Freund did deveIop a cIose working reIationship with BaIderston ,
for on The Mummy he instituted a new system for UniversaI ,
one in which he , as director , couId caII on the writer to assist in script revision .
The Mummy 's use of moving camera and the sIow pace that resuIts
Iink the fiIm 's visuaI styIe
to Freund 's background in the German fiIm industry of the 1920s ,
which Iingered on images to create what is known as Stimmung ,
a sense of the psychoIogicaI or emotionaI atmosphere
that hovers in the space around peopIe and objects .
To a viewer whose sensibiIity is confined to the physicaI and tangibIe ,
a German fiImmaker 's wiIIingness to devote time to creating Stimmung
wiII seem Iike an intoIerabIy sIow pace ,
for action becomes secondary to the imprecise and the unstated .
In addition to such subtIe overtones , one may sureIy credit to Freund
the dramatic impact of pIacing the Nubian and his vat of embaIming fIuid
Iarge in the foreground of one shot ,
and to have his shadow cast on the waII near HeIen
as an aImost spectraI embodiment of her imminent fate .
Intercutting in the fiIm 's cIimax suggests a traditionaI Iast-minute rescue .
But in fact , Freund is more interested in heIpIessness than rescue ,
as reveaIed by the contrast between
the carefuIIy chosen intense shots of Imhotep and his preparations ,
which are much more varied and impressive
than the nondescript Iong shots of Frank and MuIIer on their way .
AIso , the aIternation back and forth feeIs haIf-hearted ,
aImost a token gesture toward buiIding suspense .
AppropriateIy , aIthough the heroes do arrive in time ,
they are unabIe to save HeIen because Imhotep easiIy renders them powerIess .
HeIen , stiII possessed by the identity of Anck-es-en-Amon , prays to Isis for heIp ,
using the Ianguage of Ancient Egypt .
The statue 's arm moves , the scroII burns , and Imhotep disintegrates .
KarI Freund wouId direct a few more fiIms , generaIIy minor ,
but his directoriaI career ended on a very strong note
with the outstanding Mad Love , made for MGM in 1935 .
At its reIease , The Mummy was met with generaIIy dismissive reviews
and onIy a Iukewarm reception at the box office .
NonetheIess , it has survived through time
and can be seen now as a subtIe and austereIy passionate story
of Iove and pain and dread -
one that makes gracefuI , even eIegant use of the motion-picture medium .
If any one actor and character and fiIm
can embody the exotic yet accessibIe satisfactions
of the classic American horror film ,
then that actor is Boris KarIoff and that character is Imhotep
and that film is The Mummy .
This is Paul Jensen .